so I just want to this is Bonnie and I'm
on the phone here with steven nicholson
is that how you say you love me that's
it and steven has agreed to do me would
I consider a big favor and I think we're
going to have some fun here just to talk
about this kind of new campaign that I
posted all around the internet about
collective insight symposium and because
i don't think that what you can post on
the internet formerly really does
justice in describing something of this
nature i asked even if he could help
elicit from me some more information and
really whatever he wanted to talk about
so thanks you're entirely welcome and i
guess we said i was going to start and I
just wanted to start by and I could be
wrong in this but I think the first time
we bumped into each other was during one
of the magellan course offerings and we
were doing and offering on Goethe's
delicate empiricism and I you know and
it's funny because I think the first
time we bumped into each other has had
had the shape of the way we bump into
each other a lot and that is I posted
something that either is was that a
context or seemed out of context to you
and seemed to be highly not very
flattering tiger thur or the really neat
of what Garza was doing and somehow that
came to your attention and you responded
with i would say of piercing and very
very extraordinary naming of what gürtel
was trying to do and it was obviously
important
you that people were using Goethe and
you know just accommodating him to
whatever trip they were doing and in
that and in that process reducing them
so that that's how we started we got to
know each other and and I and I think
I've always appreciated that that aspect
of the way you show up in and around
what I'm doing because it really frames
some of the things that I'm doing and
makes me make sure I mean I don't always
represent myself the way I'd like to but
I want to make sure that I am trying to
be as real as I canon and I think that's
how we first bumped into each other just
right I think stuff too I'm vaguely
remember that I i remember that i saw
you announcing that you'd do this goethe
thing based on a book and i had read a
couple of years before a whole symposium
on Goethe's scientific method and so I
brought that to your attention as a sort
of an adjunct to your material yeah then
I got into that I got interested in it
joined up it was fun yeah we learned a
lot from it I mean I think some of the
you what I would say the insights that I
received from the 18 months that I was
doing the magellan courses that was a
big part of it was just this this aspect
of staying as close to the phenomenon as
possible and yeah and yeah this and the
material it turned out the couple of
chapters in the book that were good
we're from were represented on those
links given and then that the rest of
the book wasn't quite as interesting as
what you had offered so
to be really great and then you suffered
with us magellan courses okay well I I
like the I liked what part of da markers
saying that I could that I could attend
I couldn't attend it all in tonight and
then there was always look to her so
anyway I'm really pleased that you
wanted me to do this interview because
it speaks of a trust that doesn't
necessarily have to exist because
there's I sense there's this gulf and
off the top of my head I cannot think of
anyone who is so thoroughly different
from me than you are and this is I mean
we were born in substantially different
generations the regional culture is that
shaped our perspective might as well
been oceans apart instead of a couple
thousand cross-country miles my hair is
at least twice as long as your days
maybe three times you like cute little
Morgan horses and I like big ugly
mustangs and i will bet money that Myers
Briggs says you're an introverted
intuitive type and I'm an extroverted
sensory type you like I abstract
concepts and putting up words on a
printed screen and I like stories and
hammering solid art out of hot steel
anyway that says that's kind of a
context of this of this interview and in
your invitation to me you wrote I want
you to really grill me in the sense of
making it more real it's real to me but
then I have a way of getting lost in the
theory and I read that line and suddenly
put it in perspective with that line
from send in the clowns me here of at
last with my feet on the ground and you
in midair so we have set this up as a
collaboration on how to diminish that
space as as far as my perspective on it
goes I mean
what I would like to do and for me the
best way to start out is to review that
old cliché stick about the singer or the
song and in the first post I ever wrote
on an internet forum i said i'm here for
the singers and not two songs because
songs just come and go in this light i
want to contextualize this interview
with a brief focus on you the singer I
want to find out about a few defining
moments of your life and how they put
you here not just what you thought but
what you did to define yourself if I
just ask you your most defining self
defining moment as a young adult and
adult any time since you know you were
at least hat self-conscious what that
would be and I would like to hear you
talk about that for a few minutes and
then we can get started reviewing the
song yeah you know when I am going to
tell the story but I I do want to say
that I certainly experienced the story
as you know it's easy to construct it
looking back it certainly does not did
not feel this way going forward and when
someone asks a question like that then
you tell a story in a kind of a succinct
way so it makes a little more of a story
about it and I just so so I just want to
start with that but if i was going to
create those connect all those dots and
have a thread that made the singer the
story of the singer and or maybe the
question is why does a singer sing the
song as they do right George exam it
certainly starts very young
and when I was I asked my mom I said you
know mom when was it that you taught me
how to pray you know you kneel and you
say now I lay me down to sleep and I'm
sorry I yelled at my sister you know
this kind of thing and so she was able
to to date that for me so I was about
four years old and I had these I had two
parts of my life I had a very strange
kind of relationship with adults because
I always thought they were pretending
and I always thought that okay I'm young
and they pretend until you get to be a
certain age and then when you're a
certain age then they let you in right
they let you in and you have real
conversations with them and I was kind
of always trying to set well you know
say to my parents look you know I know
I'm young but I already know like we're
pretending and that couldn't ever really
be bridged and as I got older um I
started to realize I was like oh my god
they don't even know they're pretending
so I was probably 11 or 12 and and this
was very strange thing to me so now I
have a more sophisticated understanding
of that now in terms of the difficulty
it is to step out of roles and people do
have some kind of in many cases sense
that they are pretending but can't get
out of the roles and stuff like that but
at that time it was just a big mind blow
now the other part of my life was I was
just so naturally intuitive in nature
and naturally good of the animals you
know even today there's people bring me
their little deer that they find and the
bunny rabbits with three
eggs and if I go out anywhere by myself
especially on horseback a lot of animals
up here in presents themselves and so
this was a a dichotomy really that I
lived you know in terms of this yeah in
terms of these two different types of of
world that I lived in and I think that
dichotomy also kind of became manifest
in my personality because growing up I
was very physical I was very athletic I
was senior athlete of the year I was
sexually ravenous um but then I was also
very intellectual and able to remove
myself and see patterns in the landscape
and see the cultural construction of
things even before I started to read
things like that and so that became kind
of an interesting situation for me
because for a while I was wondering
which one is really real you know the
fact that the intellect can see the
physical manifestation made the
intellect somehow seem more real you
hear me today saying don't let the
intellect play the trump card it's just
in the soup with everything else but at
a time the way the intellect is
structured because it becomes be the
seer in our culture that makes it seem
like it's more prior or something but
the physical was more real right more
grounded so this was kind of like what
you asked me you know what was formative
in my adult young adult life and it was
just this in and and moving toward I was
ever had anyone to talk about this was a
journey I was on by myself I did not
read eclectic material I was a neuro
scientist in postgraduate work but I had
this whole other campaign that I was
always doing since I was a little kid
and then I had a series of significant
in sites where i could see clearly they
were not two poles of something that
then the dichotomy itself was socially
or intellectually or cognitively
cognitively diskin structed so i start i
spent 30 years reading philosophy to
find someone who could articulate this
and i realized that and it and you
couldn't like i'd go into the chi gong
community and see if it could get
resolved there but they hadn't biased
against intellectual you know so there
was every community i went there was you
know and then i found will burn I
thought Wilbur was going to name it but
then he ended up just resolving
everything into the two truths doctrine
so so for me this this whole complete
experience of its like the cosmic joke
like the whole thing is just is just not
a dichotomy and it's and it's so merely
the whole dichotomous nature of
everything is so clearly an elaboration
on to for me what is real so that I
think probably can't answer so much well
yeah I think it did I appreciate it a
lot the other context is that I want to
can come out of the magellan course um
perspective
and then get into you your new
enterprise you you're designing right
now like you designed the Magellan
courses this upcoming symposium and
hopefully more that will follow it and
in your ITC paper you wrote and this is
about design to design this is a quote
to design for emergent transformation
requires designing from causal
generative states of awareness this
takes the form of what I call ritualized
inquiry combined with a deep sensitivity
to what is latent latent and wants to
emerge a sensitivity which arises in the
core spaces of one selves as
universalize creative energy it is here
in the fluid flow of causal energetic
for fields generating fields and self
other worlds as a rising interfaces that
the designer must live now what does all
that mean what is ritualized inquiry
okay so yeah let's start by looking at
the small phrases ritualized inquiry is
well we're a more often involved this is
a ritualized inquiry right so we set it
up and we have a conversation it's the
interview kind of situation a lot of
what we do is virtualized inquiry and so
so it's not necessarily a strange thing
but when you design for ritualized
inquiry then you're creating maybe new
forms you know in the idea for me about
ritualized inquiry is to set up a
situation where people are as closely as
possible experiencing something new for
the first time you know it's I use the
horses like
the horses are great if people are not
used to horses at all they go down we
work with the horses then whatever
they're holding whatever they're holding
on to whatever their their interest
whatever is latent question in them you
know I'll talk about something wants to
move I don't really say that to them but
they come down and they interface with
the horses so that's a way of ritual
izing their inquiry instead of just
saying okay well what do you think's
wrong with you you know what I'm saying
all right right so like psychiatrist do
that right and and now we're too smart
for that right we lay on the couch and
which we already know what that's about
so it's no longer a ritual it's more of
a received framework and so what I mean
by ritualized inquiry something that
still sets up a situation that is that
you that the intellect won't package is
a known or a given you know so that's
hard to do in our community everybody's
done kind of everything so that's that's
that part and the sensitivity then is
the burden on the designer also has to
be sensitive to not to try to impose on
this whatever you're doing their own
knowing their own expectation of what's
going to happen but but on the other
hand I'm trying to acknowledge that
there's some design in its oh so you're
sensitive to something and you're it's a
tricky thing you know it's like you're
sensitive to something and you're trying
to keep this experience as close to a
new experience as possible so people can
see it like when their children are they
can experience it for the first time
you're trying to play a role in that but
you really can't you really have to try
to avoid understanding that role in an
own way because then you're just
collapsing it into so to give you an
example someone came and did one of my
horse workshops and it was they were
only here for a half a day and
afterwards she said well what do you
think this happened and what do you
think that happened and I said well I
wouldn't say to you what I think because
the whole reason for doing a horse
workshop is to have that process in you
in in kind of and to be sensitive to
whatever it is that's arising in you so
I can put the person in the horse
together in a certain way to better have
a better chance that that will happen
but then I also have to keep my my you
know I have a theory of why that
happened and it's based upon my
projection of who this person is and you
know that's not my place to yourself out
of that gotta keep it out of that so
that's the place where the designer has
to live you know that's when that time
kind of means they're supposed to be
poetic actually the last line is pretty
good yeah um I'm going to think about
that a little bit because I'm going to
get back to it but but I'm i have i have
more clarity now yeah and now this is
another foundational type of question in
that same paper i came across this line
that quote this is why the metaphor of
the magellan journey is so apt we cannot
expect our usual navigation devices will
give us useful answers now I want to
know what are the usual navigation
vices that you mean here and how are
they going to fail us and maybe part of
that question is what is your insight
concept of an insight standing alone and
then a collective insight and how will
they save the day how do you think they
can become navigational devices yeah at
first I want to de-emphasize save the
day and I know my campaign starts with
this kind of really you know Hollywood
charge and stuff and I do think it's
interesting and fascinating and possibly
useful but for me the major drive is fun
you know so and and I hope it attracts
people I think you can only be
successful if you enjoy the process
because I think that that saving the day
the world's going to Armageddon actually
is one of these things that is an
obstacle toward insight and creativity
so but I was right with ya but I do have
this you know kind of Hollywood
beginning to my narrative there I think
that what our usual navigation devices
for me I mean they're they could be
different for other people I find that
these are not the case with some young
people that I've met recently you know I
think that that I or my age my mic up my
age my culture my generation have
internalized some of this but usual
navigation devices like um let's see
what some would be in good context here
is that that well here's one that comes
from the campaign that that when groups
get together to work out problems that
we're going to be either in some kind of
debating comp
titian we're going to look for consensus
or we're going to compromise when you
have difference alright so those
everybody's familiar with those nobody
likes any of them so I'm saying well we
don't we're not interested in any of
them because I'm interested or this
process is interested in something that
we haven't considered before right so if
you come together with a group and you
say okay here we're not going to do
we're going to work on a problem and you
know this is an experiment so we're not
going to use this course competitively
there's no intellectual competition
you're not interested in that we're not
interested in consensus building and
we're not interested in compromise so
let's work on this problem so you've
kind of taken away the most of the
navigation devices and most and what
happens when you when I've done this in
in small groups is people start to laugh
because they realize they get stuck in
these patterns so some people are stuck
trying to get consensus some people
can't help themselves but the hit their
pattern of debate comes over and over
and over you and we start to laugh
because we see the organism is just kind
of stuck in patterns and then when you
become very aware of these patterns for
a while you kind of laugh because you
don't know where to what you can stop
them you get so you can interrupt them
but you don't know what to put in their
place and that's a transitional period
because you're waiting for some some
it's an e you know it's kind of like let
me break in here right now because this
relates to the next question I was going
to ask and you wrote in a PM to me about
dysfunctional group processes that you
have experienced and quoting from your
message says lots of dysfunctional
dynamics structures that come up energy
body patterns everywhere only some
people could see the patterns and
release them into
spontaneous creative thing other people
are straining too hard to get some kind
of spiritual eyes d'expérience and had
lots of problems with their energy body
so this was interesting to me is this
what you're talking about well those are
I think a little more sophisticated
patterns right okay the one that I just
talked about you'll find in any kind of
group prop you know board meetings I've
been an organization or business
meetings then you're going to bring in a
spiritual community that this one was
particularly talking about and you have
this another pattern and the pattern is
to feel some kind of collective
consciousness or mass consciousness or
you know I I said to the other day and I
don't know what's up with you people you
know we just spent two thousand years
deconstructing the ego in Eastern
philosophy and now we have the super we
collective being we face thing you know
and I said we're going to just spend the
rest of you know another 2,000 years
we're gonna have to deconstruct that so
that to me that the product of the same
pattern so now we can look at that as a
pattern itself and this whole week base
interbeing now I think there's something
interesting going on in those processes
but I would for me in my work I want to
use that incorporate it and be able to
make distinctions because I don't that's
not what I'm interested in let's say and
I actually think that that that some of
that work is problematic if people
aren't making the right kind of
distinctions um okay what's an energy
body you talk about energy bodies a
couple of times in this message yeah
again it's not nothing that's very
mystical there are unsure when you've
had the experience of there's some
people you walk into the room and I can
use an emotional term you know they're
just eggs up there so full with anxiety
and they're running off the wall and
stuff like but I don't need to use annum
words I just that it's just the way
their energy you know they're like and
then there's other people that you walk
in there like those room ionizers there
they're so grounded and they're open in
their eyes are open and that the way
they you know there's a whole other kind
of it it's automatic you can you know
everybody's can feel it you know so some
people are just like that person's
presence yeah their presence the energy
is a basic energy makeup and and so
that's it okay um now on your collective
in sight post on your insight blog and
you also copied this over to your
campaign literature you describe what we
know and I think that that's you and
people that you have worked with I would
imagine yeah you describe that what we
know about collective insights but but
the i found that paragraph incredibly
general and theoretical it was um not
nailed down and it didn't tell a story
or say how it was that you knew what you
knew what you know yeah and you just
said we know this so did that no income
from your experiences of someone else or
were you know before did you get them
and you don't have to endanger any
privacy of others anything no and
actually yes you know you're so you're
so i want to say this word that i type
out but i don't know so that's really
good pick up on your part writing the
text for the symposium is a little
difficult because it doesn't represent
the view of all the people that are
participating in the sub
iam and so it is kind of like not that
precise and not nailed down because the
whole point of the symposium is to take
these many different traditions that I'm
not experientially aware of and put
ourselves together and see if there are
some phenomenon or our principles like a
guardian science just to look at this
very direct you know very directly I
know some of these most of these
people's work and I've seen them
presented conferences but that we
haven't all any of us sat down together
and done this work so that's what I'm
hoping to do in the symposium is to be
able to speak in much you know safe this
is an experiment this is research this
is what I know and this is what it looks
like so but when i use the we term that
is generally i'm talking about a couple
of people who were at the third magellan
retreat who stayed to and we had some
significant insights about group process
and we started to really develop some
questions around this inquiry and so
that represents a little bit about like
tentatively we're at this point we know
these things but because it needs more
research that's why we ended up wanting
to do the symposium and I see in that
paper you also wrote that collective
insights are rare in groups and mariya
bek is how you pronounce your last name
yes wrote in a comment I agree it is
still rare it doesn't happen a lot of
times in groups but somehow it is not
special to me probably because it feels
so natural
you were experiencing it it is just of
life so in that regard it isn't special
um what what's your reaction to that
yeah this is this is why I'm fascinating
with this it's one of these subtractive
additive things and that I've been
writing about recently there's there's
an aspect i recited as a class or the
other day and he was saying well you
know it's just so much fun like if if
you are with people and you're really in
resonance and you're really thinking up
what happens is collective insight
collective insight when two kids are
like that Roy Orbison traveling Wilbury
that's a three right is that rare well
yet that level of skill it's probably
rare but there is something that I agree
with you if it seems to be something
natural now you can take a historical or
evolutionary or anthropological
perspective and in that case I don't
think that it is I don't think it's like
early man could do this right because
and there's a whole anthropological
reason for that but but certainly people
who are artists people who young kids
when you're laying on your back and
you're looking at clouds and someone
says oh look there's a panda over there
and the other person is kind of
searching around and then they kind of
see it but then they say something this
is very similar to a process a
collective insight right and and so
there is something very natural out the
problem so that's the subtractive
argument that you have to take away
these problems and these obstacles we've
learned to get back to it the question
is what is what is what has to be added
to do collective insight at the level
that adults are trying to work together
is it merely a subtraction process so
Terry o'fallon ins and
you know Ramirez are coming they've done
arguably the most work in higher stages
of cognition and states of consciousness
they would have an additive argument
right so we've got some so this is you
know I don't want to keep course I'm
plugging this imposing but this is like
for me I'm really excited about the
symposium because this is going to get
processed these this this question and
and because I have this kind of systems
thinking mind and then I can see that
these this is all part of the soup that
is fascinating to me I find it
surprising that you would think that
early man and would not know would not
be able to practice this or it wouldn't
happen I would think it would be just
the opposite i think having experienced
these collective insight moments in my
own my own life they seem instinctual
they seem like you know by looking at
your horses that they're communicating
without communicating right yeah that
it's is that an instinctual thing and
they're all in the same place well I I
think that what I suspect but this is
again what what my intention is in doing
the these experiment is that there's
there's you know it's a seamless
progression so to me there's an
evolutionary component which I call
effective resonance and this is what
you're talking about with the horses you
get down to where you're working with
feeling and energy content and there's
not a separate sense of separation and
and your kind of working with that
and I think that's essential component
of of some of this work then you have
the next step up is early man
anthropology of like tribal affiliation
and the reason why and if you look at
the forms that took then I would say
that they relied heavily on community
specific practice and the development of
of of hierarchical leadership over time
and so that's why I would argue that
that not that this didn't happen before
but it's really only emerging as a
substantial capacity now because I don't
read the anthropological record in the
same way but there's something at each
stage all the way from the you know the
mammalian bonding that is a necessary
aspect of this so that would be my
additive argument but as I said there
this is part of the inquiry hmmm yeah i
would i would think it has something to
do with basic brain chemistry haha to me
that's Alex L but yeah but and I never
looked at it might I just thought oh its
just oh this is pretty rare and this is
pretty big anyway RIA continues on her
comment and she says one thing that I
would like to stress again and again
collective insight will only happen when
the participants can spend all the not
knowing and related discomfort because
the inquiry they are in the guiding
question has enough relevance for them
that they are willing to sit it through
has this been your experience also this
is a little bit this is part of the gap
between my experience Andrea's
experience so
what I can point is that at the stage we
are at now it is uncomfortable for the
most part to do this work and and so you
asked a little before about structures
that come up so I've been in a circle
for example where we're sitting there
did an experiment we're sitting there
about 18 people and there are no rules
we say okay we're going to not have what
reacquaint it we're not going to have a
theme when that we're going to see if a
theme comes up we're not going to have
any rules we could make rules up if we
want we're just going to start with
nothing and so what happens is that full
it's kind of like like I'll give you a
little example of how I experience this
happening instead of pointing out what I
saw thought I saw on other people so
while sitting there and you know I want
to make sure that we're not going to get
into some kind of spiritual mass
consciousness so i feel myself without
anything happening I can feel myself
pushing against that but that does not
have that had risen yet and then I
remember at one point everyone was being
really quiet and I got up to go to the
bathroom and I felt like I felt like
what I did when I was in fourth grade
like do what you know like I should have
asked permission and so you can feel
these little structures arise in you and
and if you over react you get itself I
think that's that was obviously
happening to people that like these
structures were rising and then they
were they were yelling at people but but
there was nothing there they would just
these people happen to be all people
that you know like all don't you know
they've been pushing against structures
so much that when you completely take
them away then then the dynamics become
dysfunctional because everyone's are
still pushing against certain structures
and they're not even there which is for
me it was a fabulous way to witness some
this and there was a couple of young
people very young people in this well
very young 20 30 year olds in this who
were there because they in particular
were part of the movement of enough
people telling us what to do enough of
school enough of gurus and they came out
of it thinking well maybe we don't have
the capacity to live without gurus and
frameworks and structures because all
this stuff is internalized and this is
where a lot of the discomfort comes from
and so you don't necessarily for people
who have done a lot of meditation
practice you can start to feel
discomfort in your own organism but then
you when you do this with groups then
you magnify the discomfort times the
number of relational dynamics that are
pushing on you so I tell you I i left
that experiment thinking my god I don't
know how the Palestinians and the
Israelis will ever get along because
this was just a group of people who knew
each other rather in a calm ratalie
fashion and people were just it was like
feeding Christians to the Lions and some
phases of the work hmm I just I kind of
lost my train of thought because that uh
took me in a different direction then I
had anticipated going but but she but
riaz common oh yes she so in order to
survive this you need something that's
very important to the group right and
and I brought that up the other day in
in the forum where I said I mean there
has be a a material impingement done on
a group of people to get them to really
collaborate
and I take it that what you are when you
talk about collaboration you're talking
about collaborating to move in a
direction towards collective insight is
that correct yes okay and so how do you
get it at some point how do you get a
group to focus on the common relevance
that Rhea speaks about yeah I think that
what it is is I would say that the
relevant the meaning of the question has
to be have more power than the
discomfort of the path to get there okay
unless unless you're doing an experiment
like me where the discomfort itself is
part of what I'm interested in but for
if you're not if you're in the group
process so there's two ways to do it you
can either make sure you pick a theme
that has such like like you're all going
to die if we don't figure this out like
an Apollo 13 you know when Ed Harris is
working with us right so that really
gets that group to gel but you could
also work on training people to not have
the discomfort right or to understand
the discomfort and not have it have the
impact that it has and I guess that's
very exciting to me because I'd like to
broaden the scope of this work so people
could you know use it to learn in the
classroom and and and really learn it to
be a fun thing right so and I think that
these these this is something that is
very trainable and learnable
and yeah and I think that if we had a
culture that introduced this early on as
I mean we introduced competitive debate
we introduced this is what kids learn
they go to school and when there's two
different opinions one is right like the
teachers and the others wrong so that
they learn we're constantly reinforcing
a certain way for people to engage and
my point is is so we've invented these
capacities are constraints and we can
introduce new ways that have different
capacities and different strengths and
maybe they're more useful right now so
that would be my hope is to be able
through training is to reduce the
discomfort so maybe this maybe this
leads into my next question and I'm
going to use this idea of collaboration
moving towards the collective insight is
that you mentioned yesterday in your
facebook dialogue with mostly Timothy
O'Sullivan who asked you why you saw you
were designing something new in the in
the field and you mentioned various
various people who were working in group
dynamics and group processing and so on
and in mentioning riaz work you wrote
quote a rear back for exec for example
is taken auto sharma's work and over 14
years of research extending it more in
line with group process collaborative
inquiry doesn't really look at what I
call deep phenomenology and and now one
of the first of your insight blogs
as I read while preparing here was a
short one called deep phenomenology and
it is a short post and I will quote some
it might even quote all of it one of the
practices quote one of the practices we
can bring to inside training it's what I
call deep phenomenology this is the
practice of observing the subtle
dynamics of the self we can learn to
feel into the pre conceptual processes
at different levels of awareness a deep
interior core of simple presence a basic
quality of energy the feeling tone of
effect before it complex ified as a
motion the sense of the body and then
the sense of the body's relational
aspect in world space and you continued
by saying we learn we can learn to be
present within a group of people and
achieve a deeper and deeper levels of
resonance by synchronously attending to
and moving up and down through the micro
genetic stages of the self arising now
are you first of all I would like you to
bring that down a little closer to the
crowd yeah and but does is that part of
the thing of getting through the
discomfort yes it is part of the thing
of getting through the discomfort so let
me tell you what's exciting about what
RIA does she you know Otto Sharma has
done the you theory and it's had a big
impact and what he does describe them to
you is talk about the different state or
a different you know different ways the
person drops into unknowing and presence
and then comes back up and becomes
dialogic again she sees that groups go
through a pattern so groups will like
she's done 14 years of research and
there's a point at which she calls it
like the
oh there's a phase called the not the
growing phase but I forget what it is
but every group goes through all you
know the same processes basically early
on before they get to where they start
to instead of processing discomfort
start to really kind of synergize and so
she's been running around looking for
groups that can get through you know
principles that can get through you
through the several levels faster right
so she and there's something that helps
the discomfort when you know that
because you just know you're going to
have to go through this process is very
similar to when I write when I write I
write for maybe three or four weeks
maybe 40 or 50 pages and I hate it I
don't like any of it but it and then all
of a sudden I have some inspiration or
insight it usually comes either when I'm
shoveling manure or I wake up the next
day and then it's all there and even
though it's not completely
understandable what I want to say comes
right up and and yet I know I have to go
through this process of it's not like i
can just do nothing for two weeks i have
to go through this process of burning
out the stuff taking out the garbage i
call it right so in terms of deep
phenomenology it's being aware that the
organism is going to be in a pattern
especially you know we're i guess
there's maybe some highly enlightened
liberated completely free organisms out
there but the organism is going to be in
a pattern and that pattern in group
process is extended so so if if
someone's getting really really agitated
then I can feel that I can be sensitive
to wear that's affecting me or someone's
getting real
highly intellectual you know that's my
trick not my trigger it's a trap I just
jump into there and then we can go off
into like God knows where you know
people don't even know what we're
talking about so you start to see that
there is you know that you yourself or
pattern but in group process if these
things are all infectious right so it
becomes you begin to be able to be with
the system right versus that you can
feel this it's very similar to working
with horse you feel the tug or being
intuitive in the landscape you yourself
you're you're sensitive to what the
rising in you but you understand that
it's that the push and pull of part of
me wants to go this way but part of me
wants to go that way and this doesn't
feel right and that you start to feel
that it's more of a system that the
group itself go through phases and
systems and stuff like that so that
would be what I would call taking deep
phenomenology that capacity to this kind
of work certainly to see energy like the
most important one is the energy can
come up and then the emotion comes in
right away like people the energy might
rise in someone and it will default to
fear or anger right away you know it
just it's just this is the Oort pattern
of the organism sometimes um and then
you get to laugh at it because you like
geez you know it's just it's just like
if I put if I put pizza dough in the
oven at 85 degrees it's going to rise
sounds like a law of nature so you have
to get through those phases where
everything is just a pattern before you
can really be spontaneous and creative
okay um
you talk here in the last paragraph of
that quote about achieving deeper and
deeper levels of the resonance and but I
also read on your blog under the heading
called axioms of a axioms of a new
cosmology and there you write generative
complexity grows through increasing
individuation and unification not toward
synthesis and unity causal generar
generativity means we come from unity a
nexus of shared history and we grow
towards complexity now my question is
putting those two quotes together about
achieving deeper and deeper levels of
resonance and also towards not going
toward sympathy and resident of unity am
I putting oranges in an apple basket no
I think I am no so this is what's really
exciting to me okay okay and so let's
look at what we see conventionally
conventionally we see two people at the
negotiating table and they achieve
agreement discursive Lee you know they
write a contract the words all line up
they can go to court with it but in the
deeper levels effect levels they're like
I don't trust this cuz I this is why
this is why you're saying all the nice
things right so this is our conventional
reality that we try to achieve unity at
this level of discourse or signifiers or
ideas or nations you know at this level
where we should be looking where the
purpose of this as humans in my opinion
is to be unique and interface like you
and I are with different people and now
we're talking and we don't really care
if we agree we're just looking at clouds
and seeing different things
but conventionally we want agreement up
there right right add more disconnected
we you know from like this thing you
started off really nicely today saying
there's this trust there right so if
you're connected where we are naturally
in Union you know from because we're
mammals at one level and then because
we're you know then the amount of
creativity that can be maintained if the
more recently evolve levels of in that
creative imaginaries and conceptual
frameworks and with solving you know
these discursive problems that can
actually be much more creative so that's
my my guess and that's how the two of
them put together because we don't we've
allowed ourselves to be completely
disconnected at the levels you were
talking early that early man is
connected and we have replaced that in
group dynamics with rules and
regulations and an implicit peer
pressure to be all the same mass
consciousness same repel I'm a
Republican in a year that you know and
so we've kind of got it backwards it's
like it's like the cart and I think the
reason why we're always trying to have
everybody wants to have the same belief
or you know neo global capitalism is
because we're actually are now
disconnected at that part we don't trust
that we've come from unity so we're
always chasing it somewhere else and for
us and this was it insight that when I
say we that a few of us had after this
very very long experiment over three
days is that fundamentally this whole
running after a wee space or a common
belief or you know some kind of
postmodern humanist vision
of swarm consciousness is is false
consciousness because that's where we
come from and the nice thing about that
is it liberates us to be wildly diverse
in terms of our ideas at cosmologies and
they can interface in the interface of
this diverse ideas can you know it's not
going to save the world for if it's only
fun that's enough for me you know so
it's kind of like those things look like
they're a paradox because the up and
down you know your ones up side you know
you're trying to match them but one is
upside down right so if you flipped it
up then you would see oh yeah because
one was going north south and the other
one's going south north and they
actually do match and this is kind of to
me a conceptual problem with the way
we've concede some of these experiences
yes I don't know if I I don't know if I
really think that very well I think
you're getting at it I think you're
getting at it we can if we need to we
can clarify that at some other point you
wrote to me yesterday and this sort of
fits in there just after after that
explanation quote the idea is to get
people to talk about what they don't
know instead of just sharing what we
already know could you explain that some
more yeah and of course this is not the
rules of this interview because all I'm
doing is talking about what I know just
felt really bad just then um oh don't
feel badly dude it's kind of like okay
so I've tell this little story and the
story is let's say you're going to a
group BBQ right and you you raise
chickens so you've spotted a couple of
chickens and I bring in a piece of cow
and somebody else things and vegetables
and you're going to do this group stir
fry right yonex
back to leave with your piece of raw
chicken right you you expect it or
latour talks about fermentation you
you're bringing it to the thing so
something will change right so that you
you partake of something that you didn't
have when you walked in and to me this
is a good metaphor for what I would say
Collective insight process is of course
we're all going to sit together in
November and come with our own knowing
this one's done 14 years of research
that's really fascinating this one's
done eight years with cognitive studies
sentence completion touch this one's
done this this one's done that so you
got to start somewhere right but your
relationship to that is like okay so
throw it in there we're not interested
in leaving with any of that I'm not you
know I don't want you to leave with what
I know that's not the purpose and I
don't want to just receive what you know
and leave right that might be part of it
what we're looking for is something that
no one brought in and if it's kind of
it's you know it's it's like the ability
to see in that you know if you read my
work on ontological have to use your
mind you have to use your mind is the
faculty for creative imagination and and
so in that process if people are
cooperating and doing it right quote
unquote ideas are running out and some
of them are ludicrous and some of them
are interested and then every once and
well someone says that one wait what did
you say there and then somebody up you
know and then all of a sudden and then
yeah nah I made a mistake and then you
go through again but it's this it's a
very very naive spontaneous can be fun
process but if you don't if your
relationship to your own knowing is like
a commodity or or you have to win or I
need to contextualize everyone in
relationship to me then you can't you
can't do this
to work you can pretend but you're going
to get this going to be way too much
just comfort right right i can i can
understand that that what what you were
doing in this collective inside thing is
trying to come to the place that the
group can have something new just the
same way that you and I come up with
something new after sleeping on a
question all night long or something
like that do it is that correct yeah or
the d and i think that like I guess you
know we can we see it in sports we see
it in like that video the Traveling
Wilburys we experienced it in the
magellan course for example when we were
trying to come up with the logo you know
that graphic and where it started off
with my little thing was so conservative
and then it went way out and then it
went and then we ended up with something
cool you know and that process is just
it's really fun when it when it's a way
it's just fun and when you're involved
in that process if you're being honest
yep this everyone says wow I could have
never come up with that now we have more
difficulty doing this with conceptual
ideas and we have with the more innate
are like music and like art right so the
question so there's something about
definitely think it's a new capacity
something about the way we get caught up
in signifiers and Signet words to us are
too close to supposedly being the truth
and not something creative you see so if
we can see language in this course in
ideas as the same kind of creativity
then we start to be able to use that in
that realm the same way we actually have
been able to do it in other more innate
arts
okay um now I'm going to get back to the
ITC paper again and from all the
material I've read so far this is this
kind of hizmet the crux of the matter
it's quote if we can set out a rigorous
set of principles for collective insight
that is not values or worldview specific
but is methodological in scope and pro
special in practice then we have the
possibility of bringing collective
insight training into a much larger
context now am i right saying that
that's pretty much them crux of your
work here yeah that's a Crocs and it is
an if right the hypothesis just
emphasizing the experimental aspect of
this and and so that's a pretty big s
and I and we started off by talking
about Guardian science I I think it's a
guardian science type of inquiry like a
phenomenon you know I didn't use the
term or phenomenon that text but i
wanted to because that's what it seems
like to me that that would be what I
would be interested in and I think other
people are going to come to the
symposium and and you know have other
kinds of insights that will be be
equally valuable but this would be my
you know I have my one kind of
examination of the process and so is is
this is does this happen elsewhere and
and I think there are instances where
you know certainly sports so you
can say well that's never going to
happen well there's principles in in
sports let's say that can be very
helpful in bridging that that are not
value know it's very difficult because
of course there's there's competition is
different cultures and stuff like that
but there's there are some kinds of
things that certainly are more effective
at nuk not not being that being more
translatable across world views and
values so the idea is the idea is that
we have big needs or big problems or
bring solutions or you know all the lot
of the stuff that we do is very large in
scale and requires a large collaboration
and people get stuck because they have
these ways of engaging that don't seem
to carry forward the project and don't
translate across values and worldviews
yeah so that's a big hypothesis I'm
avoiding trying to name it because I
don't really know what those will be is
always yeah that would be that would be
my unknowing what I would bring is an
unknowing yeah I understand that can we
stop recording a second I sure hold on
oh my last question at least for right
now goes back to this dysfunctional
dynamics that we'd talked about in a
previous question and he wrote to me
yesterday
that you suspected some of these
dysfunctions will rise in future groups
quote I suspect the same structures will
arise perhaps we can look at them more
directly so I would like this to involve
as many people from the magellan ship is
possible to build a group that wants to
look at such things that seem to impede
what we can create imagine etc the
interpersonal dynamics provide a vehicle
the energy the enthusiasm but also the
interpersonal structures the assumptions
expectations projections etc get in the
way can you talk more about the group
that you just mentioned and sort of yeah
a new phase of Magellan yeah and and you
know I wanted to do this interview
pretty specifically for the crew and
also for people who have recently joined
is not not anything formal going on at
the Magellan courses right now so the
Magellan course is just a brief history
started because I had a day job and I
had eight weeks off lay off over the
winter because the economy is slow and
we started it as a hobby and then it got
more and more interesting and became
more and more part of my career path or
whatever you want to call it and the
first phase of it was experiment in
co-creative learning and what we did is
we used text you know we read books as a
central theme around which we could see
how we could learn together without a
lot of structure and it ended that
experiment it ended in the series of
retreats where what we've been talking
about in terms of just putting people
without a lot of structure together show
elicited some of these these relational
dynamics so what I was wanting to do
after I came back from the ITC
conference and people were pretty
excited was get this group of people
that wanted to work together but not
just do the experiment amongst the 16 of
us because this is part of what's
important to me this type of work is
being been done in small community
specific practices and it only will work
in a larger group if you can include a
much more diverse group of people now
obviously people that are on the
magellan course already selected somehow
self-selected around certain
commonalities but it's certainly a much
larger group as we know when we have
seen some of the difficulties we have
communicating so we know it's a it's a
diverse group so I want to include them
I wanted to create something that we can
carry this group forward that they might
be interested in that was less
intellectual because I know that that
was a little bit of a limiting factor in
terms of who and how we could
participate and really went into more of
this experiment in co-creating
collaborating i call it collective
insight now and the way i thought we
could do that was to have i have two
people who are going to be live-blogging
the four days of the symposium one is
going to be more of a journalistic style
the other is a theoretician in online
interactions and so that will be more
kind of a meta perspective so you get
kind of like so we'll be live-blogging
of what's going on with a group I was
hoping that a significant portion of the
magellan group would be interested this
would be a new group it would be a
private group for people are interested
in playing around with this idea of
collective insight and it would start
being this group that was part of the
blogging in some short video taping from
the symposium itself and the point is a
symposium is not there to answer all the
questions but to be the beginning of the
next experiment and to both to generate
revenue so that I can spend the next
eight months working on this and so
really commit to being able to be
present in this inquiry if people want
to join up then I have on the campaign
for forty dollars you can be part of
this group during the insight symposium
and that will be the group that I hope
becomes the new transformation of what
we started in the magellan courses and I
think that group will you know people
who are interested in this experiment
should move to that to that other
private group well we look at some of
these principles and hash out what goes
on and yes and in in you know we'll have
fun to it but of course we always have
fun but that would be the you know that
would be and i'll be writing i'll be
going to write like some principles and
and yeah and we could we could look at
my very theoretical way of saying things
and try to bring it down to something
that's useful or just you know i
discovered that the hypothesis is
seriously flawed and move on to the
something else that's it all the same to
me actually right exactly we don't
always want to be right no we're just oh
yeah go ahead now I mean for me the fun
part is moving beyond what you know you
know um how do you write the
it was interesting and this is just a
little bit for me and maybe you have a
little more insight into this to the the
traveling wilburys ape and that was put
up on that on I don't know I got it
either in my news reader Magellan course
anyway I liked it because i like the
traveling wilburys and that that group
arose spontaneously um George Harris
went to somebody and ask if there was a
recording studio around and somebody
else said I need to go get my guitar
it's over it somebody else's place and
it just all fell together and Tom Petty
ended up in there Roy Orbison and some
of some few of my favorite musicians and
it reminded me of the kind of
spontaneous arising of something that
maintains itself in that form years ago
how it works and how it doesn't work
this is a little parable on that years
ago i dropped out of college to become
the managing editor of a magazine that
was national magazine and we operated on
a collective basis it was kind of a new
left some amazing pubs poem poetry came
out of it some incredibly good art but
the principle of collective insight was
supposedly a goal and an assualt after
our holy grail of this group because we
were all there just to you know on no
hierarchy no no one telling us what to
do and so on and I was there for a year
and despite everything we did all of our
staff meetings our retreats etcetera
never in that year were was there any
collective insights generated now
occasionally some people you know would
think that we were all as one and moving
on a collective insight but afterwards
you found out that they had
misinterpreted and that the group was
just as chaos written as dumb as it
always had been now partially because of
that I left that magazine and went a
half a block away this was this is also
in Nashville Tennessee went half a block
away and got on the staff of another
magazine and there was no intention in
that group of the in that staff of doing
collective insight but here we were we
were out of totally different
backgrounds and so on just a bunch of
you know
pretty nihilistic prima donna journalist
and the energy of that group of people
was was truly generative and it was
spontaneous and so so the traveling
Wilbury thing reminded me a lot about
them took me back to that and it was
sustained and the energy and the
generativity and the feeling of unity
that was I don't know how it how it was
generated I think it was maybe because
we thought we were all prima no I
respected each other yeah Dutch Santa
mark go ahead no but this is how it
works and this is why I think there's a
lot of confusion in some of the people
around this it took me a long time to
make sure of who was saying what but
like that's how collective insight works
you can't it's not over there if you
make an object out of it like the wii
space or you know we're all going to
love each other or something you ruin it
the put it becomes poison exactly why
with my experience exactly exactly so
it's so you can't make an object out of
it and that's like in my my video it
says collective insight that's what I'm
using this word if it claims the power
the personal you know it's a it's a way
of trusting the commonality is already
there you don't have to worry about it
you have to be defensive about it and
really be spontaneous and really be
interested in curious you know and and
so and then the other thing is
everybody can have an insight like the
energy so cool you'd be like wow I know
what I'm going to do from to the next
issue but the other person doesn't say
oh I know what I'm going to do for the
next issue and you both write the same
thing you both have insights right it's
generative of all this inciting is
happening but you don't come up with the
same thing if but everybody is not you
know I mean not everybody is in complete
synchronicity but but it's insightful
for everyone it's not like one person
goes home this is uh yeah I had a matter
of perspective and now I know what's
going on and nobody else had it right so
and then this is where people get
frustrated because when you have the
group of goal for this phase where
people like yeah yeah I know it I I know
you don't need I know what you mean and
then when they start to talk about well
what do you think the diversity will
come up again and people will feel like
they've been betrayed because how could
they have this feeling that we were
really like gelling and then somebody
comes up with something different and
this is a confusion right it doesn't
this is the confusion of of what
collective insight is so that's a very
good example of what I mean by
collective insight and versus what I
call community specific practice that
makes an object out of some kind of
unification and that to me is false
consciousness good good good point um
anyway I don't have anything more to
right now yeah nothing to spend X you
know just such a good interviewer thank
you thank you very much